<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>THE TRANSCREATORS | MORE THAN TRANSLATORS | LOCALIZATION COPYWRITERS | ENGLISH | GERMAN | FRENCH</title>
    <link href="https://mpt24.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://mpt24.com" />
    <updated>2022-07-07T10:51:53+02:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Author1</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://mpt24.com</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Isn&#x27;t machine translation good enough these days?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Author1</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mpt24.com/machine-translation.html"/>
        <id>https://mpt24.com/machine-translation.html</id>

        <updated>2022-07-07T10:51:53+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://mpt24.com/media/posts/6/google_translate_example_de-en_16-9.png" alt="" />
                    Well, it depends how "over, thick and full" you want it (see above). That's a nice example of how a machine translation can be just silly. It can be useful sometimes though. It can help with email exchanges, or if&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://mpt24.com/media/posts/6/google_translate_example_de-en_16-9.png" alt="" />
                <p>Well, it depends how "over, thick and full" you want it (see above). That's a nice example of how a machine translation can be just silly. It <em>can </em>be useful sometimes though. It can help with email exchanges, or if you need to quickly translate something you're reading into your language. These are situations where everybody knows and accepts that they're going to have to work a little harder to understand what is meant, and that some things won't be immediately clear, and that some things might be completely unclear.</p>
<p>Using machine translation can be fun, when everybody's on board with it and willing to make an effort.</p>
<p>Have you noticed, however, how it is suddenly not at all fun when you are reading a piece of website text, for example, and you start to suspect that machine translation has been used for it?</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Transcreation vs. translation</title>
        <author>
            <name>Author1</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mpt24.com/what-is-transcreation.html"/>
        <id>https://mpt24.com/what-is-transcreation.html</id>

        <updated>2022-07-07T09:15:18+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://mpt24.com/media/posts/5/rise_above_the_fog6_16-9.png" alt="" />
                    Sometimes with a conventional translation, the message can get quite confused. So can the reader. What's different about transrcreation? What exactly is it? Why is a transcreated message clearer, and more powerful? Transcreation uses imagery that resonates in the minds&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://mpt24.com/media/posts/5/rise_above_the_fog6_16-9.png" alt="" />
                <p>Sometimes with a conventional translation, the message can get quite confused. So can the reader. What's different about transrcreation? What exactly is it? Why is a transcreated message clearer, and more powerful?</p>
<p>Transcreation uses imagery that resonates in the minds of the target readership. Localization copyrighting is another, possibly more self-explanatory term for transcreation. Call it what you like, it involves a whole extra level of creative input. It is the process of <em>rewriting </em>a piece of text in another language. Translation on the other hand tends to stay fairly close to the words of the source text.</p>
<p>A well transcreated piece of copy might on the face of it seem to have nothing at all to do with the source. But it will have the same effect on the readership. And evoke the emotions (culturally adjusted) necessary for them to buy in to your message.</p>
<p>Can anybody with good knowledge of both languages do it? No. You need much more than that. Even truly bilingual people (that is people who have been immersed in two languages from birth and effectively have two mother tongues) would struggle to sufficiently distance themselves from the source. Even regular straightforward translation is astonishingly difficult for those who have not spent a long time practicing.</p>
<p><strong>Transcreators need all of these things</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">To be native speakers of the target language</span></li>
<li>A lot of experience doing real commercial translations</li>
<li>A genuine fascination for language and the art of transcreation</li>
<li>The motivation and determination to go the extra mile</li>
<li>Creativity and a well-developed ability to think laterally</li>
<li>The confidence to be able to reject their own ideas</li>
<li>To NOT be under unrealistic time or economic pressure</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Would you translate this as &quot;In a train to Tirol&quot;?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Author1</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mpt24.com/in-einem-zug.html"/>
        <id>https://mpt24.com/in-einem-zug.html</id>

        <updated>2022-07-06T18:54:26+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://mpt24.com/media/posts/1/in_einem_zug_16-9.png" alt="" />
                    I have seen this sign many times and have always admired the excellent wordplay. As far as I know there is no English version of this ad, and I don't think there needs to be one. I'm pretty sure it&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://mpt24.com/media/posts/1/in_einem_zug_16-9.png" alt="" />
                <p>I have seen this sign many times and have always admired the excellent wordplay. As far as I know there is no English version of this ad, and I don't think there needs to be one. I'm pretty sure it is aimed primarily at German visitors to Tirol in Austria.</p>
<p>I'm going to try to transcreate it into English anyway, just for fun, and as a quick example of the transcreation process.</p>
<p>Right. What's the message?</p>
<ul>
<li>We encourage you to go to Tirol by train instead of by car</li>
<li>You can go directly, even from Germany</li>
</ul>
<p>The word-for-word translation "In a train to Tirol" is, of course, not a proper translation. It doesn't even transfer one of the two elements of the message contained in the German wordplay. In fact, in English it comes across as no more than a fairly pointless statement. It just hangs in the air. A normal translator might still be tempted to use it though. You can understand why if you remember that regular, jobbing translators are mostly paid per word, and as little per word as the customer or agency can get away with. On top of that, they are usually not provided with the context needed to do a proper job</p>
<p>It is clear that what makes the message stick in your head is the excellent wordplay. It reverberates in the mind. Can we find an equivalent in English? Well, although you could translate the German expression "in einem Zug" into English as "in one fell swoop" or "(all) in one go", neither is usable in this context.</p>
<p>Oh dear.</p>
<p>If we don't have a wordplay, what can we do instead that would be similar in its effect on the reader?</p>
<p>We could use a different literary device. Alliteration, for example, rather than wordplay. I have one idea. I don't like it as much as the source, but it would work, and, importantly, it is usable for the intended purpose, and it contains both elements of the message:</p>
<p>"Take the train straight to Tirol"</p>
<p>Maybe if a driver saw that a few times on a stretch of road (there are several of these ads on billboards placed along certain sections of trunk road), it might start off a brainworm (a brainworm is my own term for something that gets stuck in your head a bit like an earworm, except that it's a phrase rather than a piece of music). Hmm... I'm starting to like it more. If you say it a few times to yourself, the rhythm starts to sound like a train clacking along the track.</p>
<p>It's good to like your own ideas... but not too much!</p>
<p>If you are from the company Tirol Info, then I would like to say that you have my sincere admiration for a great strapline in German. And although my English version is probably not quite as good, I still claim copyright to it. So if you want to use it, please get in touch first.</p>
<p>And whoever you are, if you can think of something better, I'd love to know what it is. Just out of interest.</p>
<p>So, there's a quick and real example of what transcreation is all about. And it <em>is</em> rather fun, isn't it?</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Customers don&#x27;t want to work hard trying to figure out what you mean</title>
        <author>
            <name>Author1</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mpt24.com/customers-want-clarity.html"/>
        <id>https://mpt24.com/customers-want-clarity.html</id>

        <updated>2022-07-04T13:11:31+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://mpt24.com/media/posts/2/alpacas_1920x1080-2.png" alt="" />
                    Your marketing copy must be crystal clear or it risks being ignored. There are a lot of voices out there and if you are trying to sell something you need to grab and hold attention. But you already know that.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://mpt24.com/media/posts/2/alpacas_1920x1080-2.png" alt="" />
                <p>Your marketing copy must be crystal clear or it risks being ignored. There are a lot of voices out there and if you are trying to sell something you need to grab and hold attention. But you already know that. Of course you do. And I bet you take a lot of care to get the source text right in the original language. That's easy for you to do if the source language is your language. But what about the English translation? Are you sure that you are as sensitive to what might be wrong with that? Be very careful here, because sometimes the translation can look good to you because you recognize each element from the source. BUT, those elements may be completely meaningless in the English-speaking world. In fact, sometimes the translation that looks best to a native speaker of the source language is the hardest to understand for a native speaker of the target language. How can you know what is right?</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
